all right Boost number five holiday
Boost number five and we are on to Vim
we're going to learn the Vim basics in
the next hour um many of you have
already heard what to do here uh this is
going to be highly
opinionated um we are going to be doing
the viim tutor and we're going to talk
about why some of the biggest streamers
on the planet including the primagen
don't know how to use Vim so stay tuned
all right the first thing is uh when it
comes to mastering text editing choosing
the right starting Point can be profound
impact on your efficiency understanding
and the future flexibility as a
technical or developer professional
among the Myriad of editors available
learning B first opportunity advantage
to still well beyond productivity is it
hard yes is it worth it yes so people
who don't like Bim tend to be people who
don't like hard things and it's like
it's like learning to play the piano
correctly if you learn it right at the
beginning you're going to learn it right
in the long run so we're going to learn
it right and it's usually at this point
people start chiming in they talking
about their favorite thing that they
made to do Bim the game they made to
learn Bim Bim Adventures Bim tour Bim
like there's a million different things
and I'm asking you to stay with me here
okay so go back and watch the trust me
video right wax on wax off here we're
going to be waxing on and waxing off you
know ARX Rob style and I I promise you
it will have benefit for you in the long
run and I'm going to tell you why that
is uh as we go through it so first
things first how do you even learn Vim
well you you you use vimtutor that's
what you do you use vimtutor right now
and before we get into the vimtutor
thing there's a few things that I need
everybody to just understand before we
do VMT okay I mean there's switch
streamers that'll speed run a vtor and
all this stuff as if it's like the
authoritative place to learn Vim it's
absolutely not um Vim is
actually got a lot more in it even the
basics that are not covered absolutely
positive
not covered by the btor and so I am
going to talk about some of those things
as we go through the mtor and I'm going
to mention them here um I do not write
about them in detail anywhere in the
book but um you know we're we're but the
Bim tutor is still the best the best
starting point I know this I've helped
hundreds of people at this point go
through Bim and learn Bim from the tutor
only without anything else and I
overwhelmingly think it's better uh just
really quickly on the Vim Adventures
thing people that use Vim Adventures
they think they learn Vim Adventures
they don't learn viim and then they come
back to go edit a text file and they
have no idea what to do I've seen this
over and over again so we're going to
actually learn Bim by learning the
basics and and and using vimt the great
thing about it is you're actually
editing a file with Vim that's telling
you how to edit the file which is really
amazing another real reason to get
neovim by the way is because Neo's help
is exceptionally good it's way better
than the Baseline help so that if you
actually do want to use the help in Vim
um the Neo help is much better and so
there there you go that's another
positive reason to use it it's the
reason we installed it and but before we
get going on the BM T thing there's a
couple of really important things that I
want to talk about and you'll understand
very very soon why I'm talking about
these things the first thing is is that
the control left bracket combination on
your keyboard as hard as it is to hit
with both of your pinkies you got to hit
you got to get you train up your pinkies
to hit it but it is the same exact thing
as tapping the Escape key on American
keyboards if you're in a European you
might it might be harder for you to do I
I for a fact know European developers
who buy American keyboards just so they
can use control the bracket instead of
Escape somebody out there is already
writing a comment they're tapping away
saying oh you should remap JK or you
should remap this or you should remap
that or you should get a different
keyboard where you can say those are all
valid solutions to escaping uh in VI and
you'll see why it's important later but
I want to put it out there that control
left bracket is the option that works
for the most people um control I I
learned last week from a good friend of
mine on the twitch stream is an
alternative for tab I find it pretty
hard for me to hit tab I don't I I don't
like tab so I've started to use control
uh I instead of tab it's actually really
fast you're already hitting control for
so many other things that having control
after tab is a great is a great
alternative so just know that and the
last one I'm going to talk about there's
two but this is a really important one
control C control C sends a signal
interrupt to your computer on every
operating system in existence this is
not what you want in vim and neovim and
I'm going to actually full screen this
warning so a very prominent YouTubers
the primeag among them is the most he
influences thousands of people he's a
fantastic Vim contributor and streamer
he's an overall amazing human being but
he is dead wrong on the control C thing
and he's causing massive amounts of
failures in beginners who are starting
by learning to use control C instead of
escape and I'm going to show you why
right now okay so by using control C is
uh if you use control C you have stopped
yourself from using your command history
in order to navigate your command
history using VI bindings forcing you to
use eemax and this rant talks about it
if you call yourself a b person and you
simultane ly force people to use emac
mode on the command line how can you
call yourself a v person I don't
understand it let me show you what I
mean by that this because somebody's
going to find this part of the video and
they're going to want to see it but let
me show you what I mean by that okay so
so while it is true that like we're
going to learn all the editing and stuff
I promise but tempu I'm going to go
ahead and edit this file okay and I'm
doing my things and you'll notice that
it says Escape right every time I press
escape and you see it in this top of the
screen it's me doing control left
bracket okay it's me doing control left
bracket right but if you watch the
primagens do this every time instead of
seeing Escape you'll see control C there
and while it is true that you can do
control C and then do control C which
why would you do that it's like so much
harder to type anyway you know it is
true that it will work here but well let
me show you why you don't want to do it
and this is the single biggest reason
not to do it um yeah so he started with
I don't know yeah so so if you are doing
control C then watch so now I'm I'm I'm
navigating the thing okay so I have set-
oi mode and why wouldn't you if you call
yourself a Vim person how can you not
use set- oi so you do set- Obi which is
in the bash RC for the Boost in the
beginner boost and in the book it's
already there for you so you are already
in Vim mode this means that all your
emac bindings won't work it does mean
that up arrows will still work to get
through the history beginners you know
the arrows you can't see them on the
screen I'm sorry I'm pushing the up
arrow and the down arrow right but by
but you have all the power of them at
your control here and and so you know by
by if I wanted to like change modes here
so let's say I wanted to go in here and
I wanted to like edit this line I want
to say oh I don't know let's say let's
make an actual example Echo uh hello
world hello world I can't type and I do
Echo hello world right so now to go up
and edit it you know of course I do
escape and then I push you know K to go
up right if you try to do that exact
same thing using control C it doesn't do
anything it just empties this thing and
and if you actually do manage to push
escape and then up Arrow I push an
actual Escape key that time and you move
the arrow keys over here and I want to
change this so to go into insert mode I
push I which we're going to learn and
now I'm going to do you know I'm going
to change this right now in order to to
to save the and go out I have to go
escape but if I'm primagen I'm doing
control I'm doing I'm doing control C
and now I'm like totally taken out my
command is thrown away the point is very
simple do not use control C for escape
under any circumstances and teaching
beginners to do this is
irresponsible and I'm going to end it
with that I is that confrontational hell
yes it is I am tired of hearing people
tell me that they can't use set Das oi
they can't use VI mode for their history
because somebody told them to use
control C instead of instead of Escape
which you now know can be control you
know control the bracket instead okay
that's enough on that rant but obviously
I feel really strong about it I am tired
of of having to deal with people who
have learned it wrong because really big
influencers are doing it totally ass
backwards wrong so here we go create a
codebook so we're going to go ahead and
and start practicing Bim right now and
we're going to do the tutorial so the
last thing to know about um uh so the
next thing to know about when you're
doing a tutorial is that this tutorial
was made by a bunch of Colorado college
kids that were first learning Bim and so
they they felt like man wouldn't it be
great if somebody could have you know uh
a new and then and then every time that
somebody tried to get Braum to put a new
tutorial in Braum said nope that one's
fine and actually one of the things with
the neovin people that I really agree
with is that Braum was really reticent
to change and to putting anything new
out there including the tutorial yeah
had many many people suggest making a
better tutorial and he said nope that
one's just fine and I'm telling you it's
not fine it doesn't even cover the
basics so it covers some of them but it
it's got a lot to be regarded so when we
go into the MIM tutor just know it's not
perfect am I making a new one yes don't
get mad get busy I already started it
two years ago there's a new thing it's
called vtor that it's you know it's it
is the same idea you edit a file and the
file gets modified and then you it's got
all it stuff in it it's not done for
this book this time but I hopefully by
by um the end of the holiday boost I
will finished that it's it's it's
nothing fancy you don't you don't need
to make a game to teach Vim what you
need to do is replace the existing Vim
Tor which I know is a lot less sexy
because all you're really doing is
generating a file and dropping them into
the file to do the editing on the file
but make sure the content of the file is
updated so that it covers all the stuff
that modern Vim can do um and including
the stuff that basic Vim ignored with
the other Vim tour that's all you really
need there's no need for yet another
game what we need is a better vimtutor
period because it does done have a Fant
fantastic job okay so based on all of
those things let's actually go do it and
I am not going to speedrun the Vim
tutorial although I am going to do it
very quickly so there's a very strong
possibility that I'm going to screw up
something or and that you know you're
going to see my opinions come out on how
to do this and full disclosure my Vim T
ability my Vim ability I am very very
filter Centric and I'm very very search
Centric so you're going to be learning
it in my you're going to learn my style
of them my martial arts style for your
loading M and you may decide that you
want to do a bunch of other things that
are better or that better for you or
something just don't use control C
please promise me promise me you just
won't use control C that's the only
thing I'm asking okay so let's do the
rest boob
tutor uh so it's actually vimma
tutor you just run it like that audio
clipping I'm clipping because I've been
yelling sorry everybody I I I'll I'll
stop yelling into the mic the way as
badly as I have been uh I'll stop
clipping it's my bad that's that's
definitely me
clipping uh control X okay
so is it yeah if this is our video It
Doesn't
Matter yeah do you want me to redo
this we can redo it should we redo it
let me redo it without
yelling all right I'm Gonna Keep it I am
definitely in the red I'm definitely in
the red on that so
um I don't know I don't know how else to
do this I could redo it and try not to
be as
angry should I redo it we can let's
should we restart should we redo
it no you just want to go you want to
keep it Angry like
that let me didel just want to make sure
you're aware just continue all right so
mtor here it is um all right I'll I'll
talk softer now so
anyway I can't do it it not be angry
you're with headphones it sounds okay
don't worry okay um okay so what is this
doing this is making a new random file
you can see the file name right there
right and and then you press enter and
it's going to go in and it's editing the
file now my file is going completely off
the screen because my font size is
insane so I'm actually going to try to
get this to fit onto the screen uh and I
I took it down one notch so that it fits
on the screen just so you know that is
80 by 25 so you probably need to have it
at 80 which quite frankly I probably
should be uh at 80 this whole time it
just makes it easier to read when it's
lower than that so um uh for what it's
worth 80 columns is generally considered
the standard terminal WID uh and for you
know for Boomers but but it it still is
is unless you're writing it you know an
RFC for the internet it you know people
use wider things um but vimt was made
was written in an old time a much
different time and so therefore you know
it does crazy things like I don't know
like it wraps its um its par its
paragraphs and stuff and but we just
want it to look really good okay so um
we're going to go ahead and read it Bim
is a is a very powerful editor that has
many commands too many to explain such a
tutorial this tutorials designed to
describe enough of them to get you
easily going uh the approximate time is
about 30 minutes which is true it takes
you it's going to take us about an hour
but because I'm going to talk a lot but
it is about a 30 minute thing and I can
tell you confidently I sent hundreds of
people through the Vim tutor and watched
them and modified it and stuff and I
have notes someplace about all the
changes and I hopefully but I'll
remember them um so here it is attention
the commands in this lesson will modify
the text make a copy of this file to
practice on if you start a Bim tutor
this copy was made for you already
that's why you did it that way all right
it is important to remember that this
tutor is set up to to teach you how to
teach by use and again games no using it
yes the mean that means that when you
execute the commands you learn them if
you only read the text you will forget
the commands absolutely now make sure
your capsul key is not depressed and
press the J key enough times to move the
cursor so that Lesson 1.1 complet
completely fills the screen now at this
point you can push J or you can push the
down arrow but we're going to stay with
J you already know that because of the
The View stuff we did so we're going to
keep pushing J and we're going down down
down down down now one of the things I
don't like about this is that um is that
you know what I'm going to
uh I'm going to I'm going to do this
differently so that it fills the
screen yeah give me give me one second
people I'm G because I want you to see
my keystrokes
so just give me a second here I'm going
to do a modification to it um
this is I mean this is not what you
would do right I'm I'm going to actually
save it to
uh tutorial and then um and then and
then I'm going to um I'm going to reopen
it because when you run Vim tutor it
doesn't load uh your neovim Stu so that
might be a thing to do actually you guys
might want to do the same should I do it
for you should we show you what I just
did should we do that how about we how
about we do that um
all right let me let me show you what I
just did to um to to oh
boy what why is it doing that why you
why you no
work it's like just barely off I'm
trying to just stay with me stay with me
for a second here while we get this
absolutely
perfect um it's still not the right font
size I thought I could reduce F size
here I don't think I can so let
me give give me one second I'm I'm
editing my font size I'm going to turn
it down I'm going to turn it down to 38
or 39 I
guess
39 and reload my
terminal um I don't know if that worked
but we're going to find
out yep that did okay so so now now you
can see the stuff at the top okay so
let's say let's say you just opened it
let me I like like this this this step
here I I wouldn't have done this before
but I think it's probably valuable for
you so let's we're going to skip way
ahead I'm going to show you how to save
a file okay so before you do anything
else push colon
W right and then space and then temp
slash tutorial or whatever right you
could say Vim tutorial whatever you want
to call it just remember it and push
enter okay now the file is there okay
but see now if you did Bim Tor to create
the file now you can like exit out and
then you can go back to it anytime by
typing vim and then Vim tutorial
whatever one you want to do okay and why
is that because if if you set up West
term properly you're going to get the
screen key stuff at the top that's going
to show you what your keys are that
you're pressing right so and that will
show you what you're pressing so that'll
give away when you're pressing contrl C
and you shouldn't be and stuff like that
okay so mean while the rest of the the
tutorial is is the same so J I'm
spamming J as you can see I'm going JJJ
JJJ we're going to fill the whole screen
with 1.1 all right let's continue to
read uh to move the cursor press HJ K
and L Keys as indicated so you can mess
with that right
now um and you know there you go move
the cursor key around the screen until
you look comfortable hold down a j until
it repeats now you know how to move to
the next lesson using down using the
down key move to lesson 1.2 Now by down
they mean
J uh if you are ever unsure about
something on that type escape to place
you back into normal mode and you see
how it says Escape there anytime it says
escape and you can use the Escape key
I've had to do that so uh westerm and
elac both those terminals have problems
over BNC which is a remote uh visual way
to access it and and for that it doesn't
understand control up bracket I found
out even know the other terminals do so
in order to get around that I can still
just press Escape right so uh if you
need to you can always press Escape I
have seen only one person in my entire
life use the actual Escape key most of
the time they map it to something else
but most of the people that I know have
used control left bracket for all this
stuff forever uh and we we talked about
that already so let's keep going uh then
retype the command you want uh the
cursor Keys should also work uh but
using hjkl you will be able to move
around much faster once you get really
used to it so again if you're an
absolute beginner and and and you get we
we did this when we use view view is is
VI in readon mode we used it earlier in
the last session and you can just you
know use the arrow keys and just know
how to escape which is we'll get to it
uh uh ZZ and this is actually one of
those times where you're going to be
able to type other stuff um so let's
keep going
um all right so let's what's going on in
it oh you know what neim apparently is
detecting that I am in the Bim tutorial
and it's giving me help about how to
exit you see this down there type QA and
pre to enter to enter that's cool that's
that's interesting that's a neim thing
yeah the neim is detecting you're in the
tutorial and telling you how to exit I
think maybe not I I don't know let's see
no I don't know all right so here it
says exiting Vim so we're scrolling down
I'm pushing J down hope you're doing the
same are you doing the same before you
execute any of the steps below go ahead
and press Escape make sure you're in
normal mode uh okay so normal mode is
also known as control mode uh type uh
colon Q exclamation point and this is a
command I do suggest you learn I use it
all the time what it does is it saves
with I mean it exits without saving okay
and just so you know um God I don't like
that this okay uh so you could this you
can actually if you wanted to put I'm
going to put some notes here but if you
wanted to you could also do ZZ here I
mean zq okay uh and i' you've already
learned ZZ and zq they're not covered in
the Bim tutor and it's really sad
there's so many people who don't know it
it's way faster to do this uh so so
there's actually also colon X will also
all three of those commands will get you
out of there okay um this one quits
without saving zq quits without saving
and this quits without saving all right
right so then move the cursor down uh
and do the other thing now I don't know
why they didn't teach you this right now
because they're just teaching you how to
exit without saving why don't they teach
you exiting with saving probably because
they're going to teach saving down below
but um so let me just tell you what they
are right
now um okay so the the to exit with
saving is just uh qw or you know or
WQ either one that that will do I don't
ever do it
so WQ whatever one you want this lot
people do this uh I use ZZ I have my
whole life it's just way faster to type
um and so so you know I'm just going to
put if you want to save which you do
because you're doing a tutorial right so
they're probably going to teach us this
in a bit but I want you to just know it
so you already saw that they eliminated
one of the most powerful things in themm
is you know the use of ZZ to get out and
think of ZZ Top If you don't know about
it um you now know that you know how
many veterans never even learned that
it's really sad remember the cursor down
to less than 1.3 all right so press X to
delete a character super easy just from
when you're moving around the arrow keys
just put x on a thing and delete it um
so it says Okay so let's go to the
arrows below and fix them okay I'm going
to go on the C and type X and now I'm
going to go jumped on the D I'm going to
push X and then I'm going to push uh
over x x x uh X okay and and now I can
just move now see I didn't change my
mode I'm not in insert mode so I can
still move around that's really great
about um about X is that it it you know
you can just Spam it and delete stuff uh
without it changing your mode something
is probably worth noting right now the
better you get it Vim the more time you
spend in control mode and the less time
you spend in insert mode so yeah if you
haven't learned yet VI is a modal editor
which means you're either in insert or
command normal mode and we're in normal
mode right now and the X command Works
in normal mode or control mode so the
better you get the more time you spend
here and the less time you spend editing
things uh and you know moving around uh
in insert mode all right so we got that
now that Line's correct let's go to step
1.4 press I to insert text so this is
the first time that you get to learn
about how to actually change a whole
line and to add something so this is
where we're going to do I so mi I and
we're going to type insert my cursor
changes I type S and it it's actually
doing completion don't worry about that
if you have completion enabled okay and
then when we're ready when the S is done
we can press Escape right after that or
control up bracket and then we go over
here and we insert and we put an I see
it says insert down at the bottom and
then we push an i for insert and then
another to put the letter in and then we
escape okay and and it goes back up so
again I'm doing control that bracket
instead of Escape but you can't tell
because it sends exactly the same
sequence to this machine so that uh
there is text there is text missing uh
there is okay so let's do this type sum
here so right here we push I sum space
and then Escape okay let's go over here
missing text this uh this text missing
this
there is some text missing this from
this line from Escape U over insert line
Escape okay now you're I'm getting
prompted with all the the L continuation
stuff by the way uh if if you want to
know about that if I type Li I the way
to get through this is control n and p
if you go down here you can just it's
already typed right you can just Escape
if you want to have it automatically
complete for you uh is is it bad to move
all in insert mode not as a beginner but
you can't move in insert mode so let me
try let me that's a good question so
let's let's pretend this is here right
right here right so I want to do an
insert mode right so um let's see let's
get rid of um from here all right let's
try to add both of these okay from this
line right so we need to do from here
now we can do from there but then okay
so to get over here we would have to
push the arrow keys right the Keys work
in insert mode in every version of Bim
except for tiny Bim which is you only
get on Raspberry Pi or something so just
know that I mean the old even the newer
version of bi the NBI on on BSD Unix
still supports uh arrow keys in insert
mode but you can see from the bottom
left corner of the screen I am in insert
mode which means that I can't use my
navigation keys my hjk andl and the
whole value proposition of them is that
you your hands stay largely positioned
on home row
so the answer can you move in insert
mode is yes but you can't move using JK
H&L because those will type things so
this is why I mean when it's when we say
things like that you're going to be
hitting escape a lot right so whoops I I
typed the wrong one um so there this uh
from this line right so you're going to
be doing a lot of modal switches between
the two which is why people tend to
remap Escape because it's so hard to hit
Escape way up there right and we will
talk about remapping to JK
uh or to caps lock but for right now
control up bracket is your best friend
all right so uh so we can back up in
here insert space line escape and do a
thing um if some people don't like that
stuff popping up and and I I'm kind of
okay with it lately even though I was
really annoyed by it a lot before but um
that stuff is happening from completion
completion is one of the number one
reasons to do this and and particularly
to use neam and uh we'll we'll get to
that eventually but in this tutorial
when you're comfortable inserting text
move to line less than 1.5 all right so
1.5 use control a capital A I use this
all the time this says add something to
the end of the line you can be anywhere
on the line and just type a capital A
and start it puts you in insert mode at
the end of the line constantly value add
for doing this right this line and then
Escape okay let's do this one down here
capital a uh in space here dot Escape
okay now when you're comfortable pending
this go to the next thing okay um there
are other ways to do that but I'm
control a is one of the single most
valuable commands that you're going to
lose learn I'm glad I have that in there
so WQ to save and exit um so uh okay
it's
WQ uh
ZZ uh or I they should say or EZ okay so
that's what it should say because they
because way easier to type I still use w
w w um w q exclamation point or whatever
when uh I don't when I I mean um Q
exclamation call Q my fingers know it co
and Q exclamation point will quit
without saving which sometimes you want
to do you don't want to overwrite a file
or something um so anyway before reading
any of these steps make sure you read
the whole thing if you have access to
another terminal do the following
otherwise exit to and Duba so this is if
you have West term go open up a new tab
okay if you have an A West term you can
go open another tab at the Shell prompt
type this command Bim file. text enter
all right let's do that so let's open a
new file you click on a new tab however
you want to do that Vim file.txt
okay we're going to go back to the the
window it
says uh okay I didn't read all my steps
I should have right Bim is a command to
start the thing we're doing that insert
and delete the text next uh in the
previous as you learned in the previous
lessons uh let's see Vim is the command
to start the file text is the name blah
blah blah use the name of the file you
can change insert and delete text as you
learned in the previous lessons save the
file with changes and blah uh WQ if you
if you have qu okay so let's put
something in there all right so just
type something okay now we're going to
colon W I can't even do it because I
don't do it I don't ever do it I hate it
all right so otherwise you can just do
ZZ and you're
done I think ZZ is way faster you guys
if you want to do God how do people type
that
fast how do they type that fast they do
though how I'm I'm I'm trying to see if
I could get good with WQ or qw it has to
be WQ you know how many times no way
man that is so harder much harder to
type that is so much
harder that is so much harder I can't
believe people still do that people that
I know and love do this that I work with
and I'm like how the hell well that's
how I learned it God I'm so glad I
learned about ZZ I am so glad it's so
much easier oh this thing needs to die
this tutorial needs to die all right
before any of the steps uh you guys know
what to do there by the way this is at
this time I'm going to tell you about
everything you're learning in the vi
thing applies to your command history
okay so we're going to take a side note
um okay you want to go do the last
command you just did push the up Arrow
right or or or because we have set- OVI
built into the bash RC I added it to
your bash RC if if you ever get on a
system and it does not have the first
thing this is literally the First
Command I execute on any system that I
don't know any system I've never been on
on the first thing I execute is set- oi
because I want VI mode and this is what
you can try to do um uh okay so uh here
we go so you can go like this you can do
control left bracket uh up so I'm
pushing KKK and I'm pushing V JJJ and
I'm going up and down in the history and
you're going to see a bunch of other
things you can do here like searching
with Slash which we're going to learn
about and I'm going to search for tags
and it's going to find the tags line and
then I can go edit that line right and I
can execute the line if I wanted to edit
this line you know or something like
that I would have to do I'm doing
control F bracket for my escape again I
already ranted about this but if you
were to try to do this with control C it
would stop you from being able to use it
so you can't use it if your fingers have
learned incorrectly to use control uh C
instead of Escape you cannot use VI mode
for command history because you won't
you won't be able to do it so don't do
that all right that has been just a
little note to say that everything
you're learning today right now in VI
also applies to your command history
okay it applies everything about it
applies to your command history so uh so
let's keep going down we saved the file
we did that already uh next next thing
lesson one summary the cursor to move up
and down is hjk andl we got that to
start the Vim you do Vim space file name
actually in your case don't use Vim I
use VI I use VI and let me tell you why
I use VI because because I think I think
you should use uh use uh VI
instead let me tell you why people say
why are you using VI are you using Vim
I'm like yes I'm using Vim the reason I
use VI is because there are a lot of
systems that don't have viim on them
yeah believe it or not there are tens of
millions of systems that don't have them
they have VI that every single BSD
system on the planet has VI instead of
them okay so you want to use VI because
if you set V to be an alias you can have
it set it you can make it so that it
switches to Vim or it switches to neim
so if you're if you're going to edit a
file like we've been doing T VI do VI in
my opinion you should do VI file
something and if you want to see what VI
is you just type vibi is alist to the
editor it's also it's also much much
faster to type so nobody's going to tell
you this on the internet there's not a
single YouTuber out there I swear to God
if you find it put it in the comments
there's not a single YouTuber that will
tell you to use VI instead of of him
they don't even know it exists in fact
one person who shall not be named once
said that they had to take over a bunch
of this is a true story they said they
had to take over a bunch of great person
by the way they said they had to take
over a bunch of AIX Unix systems from
some old people that were retiring and
he said and I kid you not he said I had
to use this thing called
V I was like it's called VI that's what
we say we say VI um there's actually
there's actually a video of of primeag
and S and B as well this is a totally
different situation
uh I'm trying to tell you VI is a thing
it's on systems it's been around forever
you don't just have to be a boomer to
use it there are new systems new SL
systems new BSD is you know
so uh precursor to VI no it's always
been just vi vi by the way stands for
visual mode of X it's a visual mode of
the command line edor which we'll get
into later so so that's why you want to
learn uh VI as your starting thing don't
type Vim just start a Vim type type VI
and then if you have Bim it'll
automatically see nbim and it'll load it
if you don't have nbim it'll load viim
and load it if you don't have Bim it'll
load VI and load it but no matter what
you're on no matter what container
you're on no matter what Raspberry Pi
device you're on it'll always
work so why wouldn't you why wouldn't
you want to burn that into your memory
that's what you should do uh okay so
exiting Bim is uh super easy so the only
time I do this one is because zq is
ridiculously hard to type for me I have
a hard time typing zq
I have a it's easier for me to type
colon Q I actually have that pretty well
memorized to quit without saving colon Q
exclamation point I have that really my
fingers know that one really well I can
hit that all the time really reliably
it's not too hard to hit um is zq faster
yes but it requires this kind of magic
with my pinky that I am not as good at
doing you you do you you find out what's
better but um uh but the WQ is
completely unnecessary an AR type and
then uh uh so you're going to say uh
it's easy to to save the changes okay
you can you can pick which team you want
to be on I still think the ezy top team
is better just just do there the thing
that says you can't do WQ for this and
then this those that's fine uh yeah
anyway so to delete to delete the
character you're already doing Co and W
all the time to save so anytime you're
afraid of saving something we're going
to I'm jumping ahead if you want to save
something you're going to see me if you
ever watch me code you'll see me doing
W like like sort of nervously all
the time because that saves your current
buffer so if you do Co and W all the
time that just saves whatever you have
and it writes it if you don't do that
it's just in memory and your changes
don't get saved so you'll see me wcing
like for the heck of it all the time and
this is one of the reasons that people
would say that just adding a q to the
end is not that hard and I could see
doing that if you want to learn how to
do that so instead of W uh you do WQ
because you've already know W right and
so it's easier to remember you do you I
I'm still as easy person uh so if you're
going to switch to war would you need
something REM BC I don't know I don't
think Dak is compatible with them period
um a lot of people like dwak I don't see
why you would use Dak at all U but a lot
of people really love it um anyway
so I I'm not going to hate on you if you
want to do that a lot of people were
really really good and fast I just viim
was not made for D key board the end I
don't I don't know what else to say
there um to Le the sound to delete the
Cur the key under the cursor is X okay
we got that uh insert or aend you push
you push I and then something and then
Escape uh and then uh Ain to the end of
something control a uh I'm sorry capital
A and then we go down to lesson two so
we have a lot of lessons to go through I
think we have seven total lessons so I'm
going to take it out we got 37 minutes
into this video um the deletion commands
Okay so this is the commands that are
really powerful uh DW I almost never use
though so DW you can go on a word
anywhere on the word and DW will close
will delete to the end of the word right
so this is actually really powerful type
DW and the word will disappear the
letter D will appear on the line of the
screen let's see uh there are some words
that let's see there are some words fun
that don't belong paper in this sentence
there are some word fun okay so we get
on the beginning of the word and then we
type uh DW and and that don't belong
here I do use this that belong paper DW
gone okay and that's really powerful you
notice it doesn't go into insert mode
all right so uh so there we go repeat
steps three and four until the sentence
is good so we we got that DW is in the
house um uh D dollar is is actually
stupid you should just use capital I
don't know why people put this in here
this drives me nuts okay this is
actually this is this is a really really
solid example of a newbie making the
tutorial okay because I mean why not so
okay I'm kind of getting ahead of myself
there's already a Capital C to change
the entire line to the end of the line
so why not use capital D it's to change
to the end of the line D dollar does the
same that says change from here to the
end of the line right so type D dollar
to delete to delete to the end of line
okay somebody typed to the end of line
twice so we go over here and we do D
dollar but that is so ridiculously hard
to type compared to Capital D this is
such a newbie
tutorial people don't do this don't use
I'm not even delete that from your brain
and your muscle memory never use DW d d
dollar sign who the who wants to type
that who wants to typee that that is
totally unnecessary type a capital D
like a non- noob oh my God I got to make
a new tutorial don't get mad get busy
don't get mad get busy capital D people
it's way easier why the hell are they
not teaching you
that don't know don't know don't care
now you know at least you know okay
please spread the word I why the hell
would you do dshift dollar that is so
much harder to
type it it stands for Deb stands for
delete to the end of the line dollar
sign means the end of the line carrot
means the beginning of the line that's
so knowing positional commands is a
thing okay that's a thing right but it's
still useless in this case is totally
useless capital D deletes to the end of
the line
deed all right so it's trying to say oh
you want to do something to the end of
the line right same thing is changing C
dollar would change to the the line
right the same thing don't do it just
don't do it do capital D oh my God okay
I I I'm done I got to move on I got any
can I have some
coffee I still haven't recovered from
how how stupid this tutorial is it's
completely lame all right so here we go
D motion all right so uh the reason is
the m the reason they did D dollar is
they're trying to teach you about motion
commands right so if you add something
okay first of all I'm just going to cut
to the chase all of this delete like
five exact words after you nobody does
that nobody does that it's so much
easier to delete until the next keyword
match then it is to remember all the
crap from the next three lessons about
navigating in Vim all right so so here
we go we're going to go down here um
yeah so here we go D motion where D is
the delete operator motion is the
operation all right uh short words in
motion W I can't even tell you how many
times I forget the W and the e e is to
the end of the word isn't you know what
I never do that I never do it full P
disclosure you know what I do I remember
T which gives me up until the next thing
that I want to type so let's say I want
to type I want to delete up into the
capital e d uh T capital
E this this whole thing about knowing
how many how many words and all that
nobody does that nobody got time
for that I'm not going to sit there and
count how many lines or how many words
there are I'm going to look at the thing
and I'm going to delete until that thing
comes up let me show you so this
basically what I'm trying to tell you is
the entire premise of motion based on
the number of things requires you to
count those things and nobody ain't got
no time for that I don't need to count
anything if I know what the unique
beginning of the thing is in this case I
want to delete Del everything up to
excluding okay yeah in this case I want
to delete up to excluding watch what I
can do d/ ex enter and it deletes all
the way up until the match and it shows
me in red what it's going to delete to
while I'm typing it why would you not do
that I don't understand I don't
understand why you would go through all
the hassle of memorizing this uh yeah so
it's like I you know I'm not using any
of these things do I want to delete to
the end of the line no I don't need to
remember the dollar ever ever ever ever
ever the only time I ever need to know
the dollar is if I'm doing something you
know in Ed which X you don't even know
which is the X command line but for
right now you don't need to know it if I
need to delad to the end of the line
it's this any if I want to the only time
I ever want to do something to the end
of the line is either delete the whole
line or or change to the end of the line
I don't care about anything else I don't
so forget about this demotion crap
Nobody Does this nobody does this it's
too slow but they don't know because
they're beginners oh de will delete from
the cursor to the end of the word you
know what else will delete from the
cursor to the end of the word that works
everywhere all right so fine d t space
that deleted to the next space so you
know or if I wanted to delete word it'
be d word I do I use DW all the time
because it's just this the current word
and and it's what you usually want
because it deletes up and it gets rid of
the space so DW I do use all the time uh
this other stuff de I don't even know
what that does it leaves the space there
like why would I ever do that if you
want to do that fine I don't I'm telling
you my take all right using using using
account promotion okay this is
occasionally valuable but but not
usually not usually you know why because
you always have to count so like if if I
want to delete two words okay so it' be
two DW that would delete two words right
you can also do two you can also D2 W
which will do the same thing just for
Just For The Mention Of of this I almost
always put the number in front just
because of uh because it's just so much
easier Ultra andano you agree with this
okay so you know it's um so let's like
if I want to delete three words I could
do d3w if I wanted I could do 3DW if I
wanted but I'm not going to do that
because I don't want to count the words
I want to delete until the word motion
so I'm going to do this D SL motion
enter and now I'm done and the word that
it went to is still highlighted and now
I can undo that that's always easier
it's easier it's easier on your brain
it's easier because everything you do is
search Centric my entire workflow is is
search Centric uh it's my entire
workflow is search Centric whether it be
searching the internet from the
commandline terminal or it's like
editing things or it's opening
applications it's always search Centric
because that's just how our brains work
and it's only one thing you have to
remember how do I get my cursor to the
next thing that's it it's all you have
to remember you don't have to remember
all the other crap so skip this whole
section you don't need that using
account account using a account to
delete more words TDW I just told you
about that you've done it already
operating on a line okay so this is very
valuable and you'll do this a lot and
I'm going to give Prime credit here I
did not know about dap until I watched
the primagens videos and so I you know I
trashed on Prime for using controls
interrupt for for escape and now I'm
praising him for teaching me dap it's
one of the most most powerful most
important things that I've ever used and
we're going to get there in a second but
but it's related to DD so DD gets you
the line it deletes the line and right
away YY just Yanks the line so DD
deletes the line and then escape and by
the way how do you undo youu they're
going to show you that later but DD and
you want to add it back Escape you
escape you for undo okay so roses are
red okay DD V are blue DD clock's ta
time uh DD DD sugar is sweet and so you
okay whatever uh double so so DD is a
thing right and and I do it all the time
what I was going to show you about dap
though and I'm going to jump ahead right
now so if I want to delete this whole
paragraph up to the next blank line dap
and it just it gets the whole thing and
then I can grab it all back this is so
valuable you will use it and it will
grab the paragraph from wherever you are
so like you could be down here in the
middle and you dap and you want to say I
want to put it here and then you P to
past it up there dap and you tast it
down here so you want to memorize that
one DD and DAP in fact even sometimes
unless I know I just want a single line
deleted I I usually use dap for
everything because it's just so much
easier to remember uh it's not covered
at all in this tutorial by the way
there's no use of it at all the undo
command we already did it control U so
just undo u and you you have multiple
undos um they don't mention it I don't
think at all but the redo command I'm
going to go ahead and tell you about
right now sometimes you undo a thing
that you want to redo and that is
actually controlr and that's a little
bit harder to remember okay so let's say
you deleted so
controlr undo undoes your undos does
that make sense okay I guarantee you're
going to need to know that at some point
it's not written here so and all of this
stuff that we're talking about right now
I want you to go back and watch the
video the first thing we're going to do
after we do this is we're going to
create a notebook to take notes and then
you need to go into that notebook and
you need to put all of this in there
because you're going to forget it all
right undo the undos all right so
operating on lines we did that the undo
command we just learned about it's just
Escape you oh wait it did teach you
about R okay it does it's right there
now control R will get you if you to
redo the commands uh okay so we're not
going to even bother with that lesson to
summary uh all the deletes don't do any
of that the only thing to remember here
DW is good all right just remember DW
this one delete delete just do that wait
this one don't do that do this do
capital D
instead uh that's better there I did it
the undo Tre is goed it really is it is
and it's long actually so uh so DW blah
blah blah all right so that's what you
should do forget what it said before uh
to delete the motion forend tww yeah but
nobody it's usually better to just do a
DW and then do and then just hit period
they haven't talked about that yet but
let me let me show you what I mean by
that all right so you know have to
remember any of the numbers if you know
about the period we're going to get to
the period later but let me but let me
go ahead and have you try it right now
so you're in the middle you're in the
word and you want to delete this word
right and you might want a word but you
you don't want to count how many words
it is right and you're super lazy you
have a fast terminal you've got you know
West ter is the fastest termal on the
planet and you're you're okay with
spamming a command so then you just you
just remember DW and then you hit period
period period period which just repeats
the last thing so now you're fine you
don't even have to do it DD okay
who cares now I can just hit period
period period And I just keep doing the
last command you're going to be using
the period for everything and if you do
that you don't need to screw around with
a stupid numbers navigation you notice I
never have I never have line numbers I
don't need line numbers anytime I ever
need a line number I have it down here
if down here in the bottom right if I
really need it otherwise I don't want to
see that crap they have fancy line
numbers that show you how many you're
going to go to and cut and paste up to
that thing you know what you don't need
any of that if you're using search
Centric VI usage so so we're going to go
down to the next thing uh that's the
lesson
summary um to undo all the changes on
the line capital u I've never once used
capital u I've never once used that
don't do that that's a waste of time
don't do that you want to limit the
number of things just use U and R the
end and you almost never need R it's
only like if you screw up like really
really screw up if you usually you it's
going to be fine like you overly you
know deleted something or something the
put command Okay so P use this
constantly right P takes whatever was
the last thing that was deleted and
pastes it that's it that's it it takes
whatever the last thing that was deleted
and paste it and so uh can you learn two
violets are blue intelligence is red
roses are red so DD space and then we're
going up and then P right can you learn
to bi dd p remember it place after the
current line which is kind of hard to
remember you'll see me do this all the
time let me show you a specific example
of me doing this when I'm when I like
modifying what my chat my thing is about
I'll go say I'll go DD paste and now
whatever's on the top line becomes my
new status right so I can go over here
and I want to put this line up and I can
I can just put it up there and I just
paste it okay so that's what that's
about so so that's p is a big one you're
going to use it a lot you should use it
I hate relative numbers people use
relative numbers I do not understand you
I relative numbers are insanely dumb I
don't like them I I would rather use uh
I would rather use the actual line
number or I'd rather use a search term
and in which case you can like search
backwards with exclamation point so like
let me say let's say I wanted to uh
delete everything from here up to type
so I do D question mark type and that'll
delete everything up to the last type
right if I wanted to get all of the
lines because there's multiple lines in
between them I go to the line that I
want want which is like 374 and I go to
the line I want and yes that's slower I
don't care and then I'm going to do D to
374 go and it deletes the whole thing
that is that slightly slower than doing
relative numbers fine uh paste below P
paste uh above major powerful and Bim oh
right capital P is something I could
probably use more of actually yes uh in
fact Let me let me try that you know
what I'm glad you mentioned that I don't
use capital P nearly
enough and that's the great thing right
I don't use capital P nearly enough this
is actually a problem right so let's say
I want to put walking the dog on the
first line right so I go I go DD to cut
by walking the dog I go up to the first
line but I can't go above so capital P
would insert it above the line versus
lowercase p which would insert it after
the line so that actually is something I
don't do very much that I need to do
more I I don't I've never really used
capital P but I could see it being very
very powerful that's I'm glad you
mentioned it thank you for mentioning
that that would be a really great use
case that actually makes my life a lot a
lot simpler by using capital P capital P
puts something above and and lower puts
it below and I I don't think that's
covered in the tutorial honestly it's
not it's not it P's just like it doesn't
cover capital P so that might be one of
the reasons I missed it I don't know uh
same power for capital A and capital e
at the beginning of the line yeah if
you're if you're into inserting in the
front of a line and the front of a word
or at the end of a word um like if you
want to insert at the end of this word
you could type a uh oopsie that's not
that's not it it's um or I'm sorry it's
e e e is it e e just moves to the end of
the word right right right uh yeah e e e
oh boy I don't know about that I don't
know if I I don't know if that's what I
want to use uh copy to macro moove lines
I'm use it for yours oh right right
right well there you go so so the
replace command so uh RX to replace the
character of the cursor x uh at the
cursor with X so R is actually really
nice I use it all the time uh so r y the
thing that's nice about it is you don't
have to um exit you don't have to go
into insert mode insert mode would be
like let's do that same thing if we were
using insert mode right so you could do
this you could say XX i y p and get the
same and escape and get the same thing
right you could get the same thing by
doing that uh or you could just do
replace y replace p and then keep going
on your about your business right while
we're at it I want to cover one thing
that is not covered by the tutorial and
that is how to fold the case so let's
say this happens all the time you want
to like change the case here and that is
TIY so if you tilt if it's a Tity the
the squiggle right under the Escape key
the squiggle that automatically folds
the case and it's repetitive
so uh that's repetitive so like you can
hold it down and if you want to make
something all upper case it'll just fold
the case it'll do the whole line for you
you got to be careful because if there's
upper cases on there it'll it'll do it
um and you that's also positional and
stuff I usually just Spam it but that
that is something that's like really
valuable especially in go where cases
and you know if you want to export a
variable it has to be upper case uh
initial case and so you know that's
that's actually a thing you can do um
it's kind of been the same line with all
the replace thing like the way to do
that if you didn't have that would be
and by the way you know there's faster
ways to navigate the line I'm I just
don't mind spamming so you could do RW
right and that would be the same thing
but if you know that you're just
changing the case you can just do you
can do the the the TIY there um all
right so next let's get on to change
operator all right so the change
operator does the same as D the change
operator is exactly the same as D except
for removing it it it bumps you into
insert mode that's the only difference
in every other way it's the same as the
D command and that goes for capital D
and capital c so like C would change the
current the current to the current the
beginning of the current word uh I don't
ever use this command ever my fingers
don't even know it it seems really
stupid to me because I wouldn't use it I
would maybe use
CW I use CW
maybe but honestly I don't even do that
I do I do God I can't even remember what
I
do I do yeah I do I do c
C2 and sometimes I want to change like
more than that what if I want to do c
marked right I don't I don't care about
the word specific things because I am
always doing d slash let's say I want to
delete up to marked D slm
marked that's what I do I'm a Searcher
I'm a Searcher and people might not like
that but it works for everything it
works for everything people so you like
like if I want to do this I can do d/s
and it'll do up to the
process you know and and the thing I
like is it shows me what it's going to
delete up to so I D slir it's like okay
yeah I want to go to that and then if it
and you know maybe not what if I want to
do D cursor okay it's going to delete
all the way to the next cursor line so
my preferred method is to do D and C or
whatever with a slash immediately after
that and then the search term because
I'm already doing searches for all kinds
of other stuff and and and that's by the
way to get rid of the search term is
control uh L which rewrites your screen
and undo the Search terms uh in my bmrc
the one that you're using so so that's
CE um change inside word I why why would
I do
that what purpose does that have I I
mean I I don't understand that I I maybe
you
yeah I mean maybe you could convince me
change in side
word I mean I guess I could do that side
word yeah I don't I I don't know why not
just CW if you're going to do
that CW oh I see because you're like
you're in the middle of the word and you
don't want to go to the beginning of it
I see I
see
yeah learn the B language
yes yes uh uh
so yep
so CI CI uh I don't even know what that
is I don't I don't do that yeah that
would be like everything inside of the
thing I can see ciw CI the thing I like
about ciw is it's like in the middle of
the word so if you're in the middle of
it you don't have to go to the beginning
of the word
right yeah I can see doing that I might
have to add that to my list
c yeah I might have to add that to my
list C IW I mean I'm already using IF
for internal inside a function and stuff
so this is supposed to be for beginners
so just nobody does CE I'm just telling
you they don't so they might do ciw to
change the current word uh or they might
do c SL marked to change up to the next
to the next word and then type stuff in
and then do the next thing uh or not so
all right so the replace command we got
uh we got the change
operator uh more changes using C okay
this whole C plus the number of motion
things don't don't do this don't do this
people plus don't ever do c this type c
dollar to change to the x no don't do
that do Capital C Capital C Capital C
instead of that it's way better okay I I
don't even want to justify that
section uh uh I code where did I start
we're talking about right now click on
the book and start there uh you're in
Holiday Boost number four of how to
learn to code you know you have a CS
degree don't add a code yep pleas this
regular problem maybe go watch the
beginner boost the holiday boost we're
learning how to code somebody new just
join our chat on Twitch all right so put
back uh to put back text that has just
been deleted uh P dot this puts just
deleted after the
thing okay so let's do this uh diw wait
let me do that DW
p no that's fine replace this is fine
see none of that is any relevance
Control G shows you the location okay
this is a one I always forget um you
don't really need this because I have it
down in the bottom on my screen but
sometimes you might want to do that
so um usually unnecessary not worth
learning um capital G to move to a a
line number is Val Val though so um so
by the way GG does not exist does not
work in VI it only works in Vim a lot of
these things are Vim isms by the way um
so so what you could do here so let's
say I want to move if I know the line
number right if I know the line number
is 487 I can go down here and I can do G
whoops I can do
487 G and that will take me to line 47
the only time I use that is when I have
an error message that tells me the exact
line number and when I open up that file
I actually do that and I will type the
number and then capital G didn't go to
that thing Capital G's by itself goes to
the end of the file right uh two small
G's goes to the beginning of the file
which is weird so capital G goes to the
end and two G's goes to the top capital
G goes to the end two G's goes to the
top okay and we're going to go search
for uh that so I can find it
again uh see if I can find a next the
capital G let me go see if I can find a
G by itself yeah there it is okay um
capital G there we go so we found it uh
it's yeah so so so here you go uh type G
to move to line in the file um write the
entire lesson before executing any of
the
steps um uh hold down the control keys
and press G uh we call control e message
will
appear and you may see the cursor
position in the lower right so there we
go there's G and G this is actually
worth learning uh I use line numbers
personally myself that's what I use the
most too 234 is what I use I don't use G
um that's what I prefer that is aism by
the way that does not work oh no that no
that does that's that is a VI thing
actually I think capital G is
aism I think it is I think capital G and
GG are Vim isms whereas if you type the
in the line number it will go to
the line number I think that actually
works in Ed and X as well so that is
like way better to learn than G and
GG
yeah that is like so much better to
learn that is so I'm so glad you
mentioned that Code Monkey I am so glad
you mentioned that because that is so
much superi that is so Superior to
Capital G right so uh it's like you know
let's like not do that let's say so uh
the line to the in the file to move okay
but capital G does go to the end of the
of the file I think uh I think
uh I wonder if
um yeah so you could just do colon colon
uh percent goes to the end of the file
and colon zero goes to the beginning you
know what I love about that is that
works everywhere God this tutorial has
got to die it is so full of stupid
unnecessary vimis that are and then it
doesn't even have consistent vimis it's
it's so bad I I really have to I've
started replacing it I got to finish I'm
Cod monkey thank you so much for
reminding us that those commands are
easier and compatible with
X so why would you learn that stupid
bism I know because you know the college
kids who made this tutorial didn't know
what the hell to do they had never even
heard of it so how to control down this
go ahead and do it um the search command
okay this is the most important thing in
the entire thing to learn is searching
because search is going to help you find
your way through the entire thing
multiple times so it's the slash is
forward question mark is backwards okay
so you can do slash enter and it'll go
right there right and then you push n to
find the next one and you'll just wrap
around and it'll find all the enters
okay if I want to go backwards I do
shift n and it goes up up up up up up up
up up right most of the time I don't
even bother with a question with the
with the question mark alternative
because why I can always go do a forward
search and then I can just hold shift
down and do the upper search okay so so
if we do search for search this is so
important because let me show you why
this you're going to use this all the
time from the history so so like if
you're doing this um let's see search
for search
uh set
option uh
search let's see let's see copy and
paste another way to replace e lowercase
aen command wait where did it go what
was it what section were we on some
command structure is
interesting yeah yeah some of the MS I
agree so I don't I don't know where
where it is oh there it is the search
command Okay so so you see how I just
found it I don't even have to care where
I am in the file I just had to type SL
Capital search as long as I can remember
so the reason this is important is that
my brain is constantly thinking where do
I have to go and what was the unique
word that was associated with it I don't
have to do the math about what page it
was on or whether it's multiple pages of
text or anything I'm constantly see
thinking about what to search for and
and that helps me with everything that I
do so it help it's also the same way let
me show you how this particular
technique has direct bearing in set-- oi
so I know people that use Zell for
completion and all this other fancy
stuff they don't know Vim they don't
know how to use Vim on command line all
I have to do is do tags and whoops tags
and I found the get push I found my
command for this one based on what I
found I don't want zshell guessing what
I'm going to use based on what I'm
typing I know that I entered a command
at some point that has a thing in it I
want to find out my last clone command
now I want to go see the next clone
command and and and n and and now I'm
going to go back up in history control
capital n capital n capital n capital N
so if I know it's like hm I know I did a
get command for something like that I
need to go find it SLG and now I can go
back up and I can go see I can progress
forward and see all of the different git
commands as fast as I want I can hold it
down and go through the whole thing and
I can treat my command history as a Bim
as a huge Bim file I cannot overstate
how powerful this is this is so
ridiculously powerful because you can go
back up and modify them you can reuse
the same things you can have everything
changed within the thing you you can't
do that in emac mode I mean you can but
it's not nearly as powerful so so you
know you can go up and go find a
different thing like this and you can
you know you can see I want to see all
the things right so and then you know
you have to and then when you if you
don't want to edit those things now use
control C why do you use control- C
because you actually want to use control
C you want to you don't want the ex the
command to execute you you want to
interrupt the command as opposed to
having it be Escape because it's a you
know which is another reason you should
use control C for escape when you're
editing bi okay so now you've got search
you know how to do search and you should
use it I do occasionally use um I do
this is the whole n and end thing I just
showed you I do occasionally use a
question mark if I know that the first
search has to go to the top but it's
very rare that I'll do that it's usually
usually that's the kind of thing where
like if I know I'm on a file and I'm
like 5 you know 530 whatever and I'll be
like uh okay so let me go to like 500
and and then I want a copy to 530 you
know and I can I can do that there
people use visual mode for that too and
and I don't and we'll talk about visual
mode in a bit knowing how to do search
you can combine search with everything
else so let's say I want to search I
mean you can combine it to to delete and
I mean you can just combine it with
everything so um and match par
parentheses is absolutely the next most
important thing and that says find to
the next blank line all right and so um
yeah this not this one I don't use this
one ever so this one searches for the
next matching parentheses or something
like that I never use this if you want
to use this that's fine what I thought
this was was the was the curly bracket
which which actually searches till the
end of a section okay which is actually
way way more powerful so if you want to
grab to the next section in this case
it's just a line but let's say let's say
this had multiple lines on it right if I
want to grab that whole thing I could
just do dap or I could do this I could
do I could do D and then I could do
Capital I'm sorry uh right curly bracket
and that that that selects until the
next blank line and so so that is
actually useful I usually use dap or or
Yap which Yanks and I don't they haven't
covered yank yet but we're going to get
there if you don't want to delete a line
and you just want to yank it you can do
y y and then ppppp and then just make a
copy of the line Okay so so you're
definitely going to need to learn that
uh so try that out um what are we on
we're on an hour and 10 minutes and
we're still not done and we got still
several more to do I'm going to go I'm
just going to power through so the preny
search don't even bother it's completely
useless Nobody Does it it's it's really
hard to hit if you want to do it fine uh
The Substitute command this you will use
I don't understand why they put this
extremely complicated X command in this
tutorial for beginners but this is how
this you're going to use this all the
time by the way it doesn't have to be
slashes it can be commas like this so
you can do it however you want um and
and this actually does work one of the
cool things about this is if you're
using NE it will show you what's being
replaced as you type it so you type
colon you type S slash or comma if you I
prefer comma a lot of times because I'm
usually changing things with slashes in
it and then I'm going to say okay I want
to find all the news uh and I want to
change them you know with something
else uh whoopsie oops I may try again uh
s oh wait okay okay so all right
um you know what's interesting about
this I just noticed oh I think I found a
quirk yeah this doesn't do
it it doesn't do it that's so
interesting huh okay so if you do
[Music]
what that is so
interesting that is so interesting okay
so this is this is a neovim and aism
that is not covered
here I I just realized something okay so
this do not do this never do this always
do
this why why would you you guys just saw
why unless you put the percent in there
you don't get the dynamic changing
showing you
watch what happens if you if you inject
the percent by the way what does the
percent mean it means do this thing to
the whole file and the colon means it's
an X command which we'll get to some
other point so um yeah slash yeah is the
major power of the US keyboard it is um
so so so here we I mean I think that's
probably why a lot of people use the US
keyboard for the searching so anyway if
if you're doing it like this now if you
do it with a percent watch what happens
if if if I don't do with a percent I
have a feeling it will work so we're
going to change um old to new G and okay
that that does seem like it did it but
it's not nearly as powerful as this
version of it colon
percent right s old new you see what it
did it actually did it dynamically it
did it dynamically and showed you what
it was doing
and and you can push you know you can
push SLG and then it does it to two of
them you see what I'm saying so the this
this tutorial is totally bad because
it's not it's not even nearly limiting
the advantage of using the percent if
you use a percent um yeah colus is is
dot ISS not the dot current line oh is
it just the current line okay never mind
okay if that's only on the current line
then that explains a lot okay thank you
thank you for thank you thank youis I I
got that totally wrong I never obviously
I never do that I I see what that's
about that's like if you want to limit
your scope to the current line we'll do
the whole file is a dangerous Zone yeah
I see what you're saying I see what
you're saying okay yeah no I take it
back so let's let's actually rethink
that one and go back and doing what it
was saying so it was saying s is only on
the current line um I wonder though if
it will actually be smart enough to do
what does this one say okay to change
Curr blah blah blah
okay yeah here we go so so here it's now
it's telling you everything in the file
um in the whole file
um defines occurrences uh between a
certain segment you don't almost never
do that you can do this but it's usually
more valuable to do that and to say I
want to do it in this paragraph and for
that you can do exclamation point uh
left bracket and then back out the
exclamation point the reason for that is
because you're going to be doing the
filter command a lot you're going to be
doing the filter command a lot and they
don't even cover the filter command here
so this the most powerful command in all
of VI is site searching and they don't
even cover it I don't understand it but
we're going to move on so so here we go
that's replacing the thing we got that
um and that's a lot to cover lesson five
oh no here's the filter command okay but
they don't they're do okay the
difference is is they're not doing as a
filter they're doing it they're doing it
as an external command instead of a
filter which is really too bad okay and
I did a whole thing on the magic of VI
and this is the single most powerful
thing in VI beside searching so notti to
type the exclamation point as allows to
execute external shell blah blah blah
okay so what why do you care right uh it
lets you run the command but unless it's
modifying the file in some case you
don't care so it says uh says a cur to
the bottom of the screen this allows you
to enter the command line uh now enter
the exclamation this allows you to
execute any external shell command who
cares I can go over here and do an
external shell command I don't need this
right I don't need this I don't need to
do a sh Comm people used to use this to
like run a compiler or something like
that you don't need it you don't need it
so um so example run LS and then be done
like why would you do this this makes
absolutely no sense oh hey I got to see
all the files okay now I'm going to go
back why not why not just open up a
terminal and do LS and then switch back
I it doesn't make any sense in modern
usage what does make sense and what they
should have covered here instead is the
filter command which they don't cover
it's so stupid okay watch so using the
filter
command Okay
um is yeah but that's that's I'm going
to do that in a much easier way right so
the the way to do that is to do this
bang bang bash and then just memorize it
friends I'm telling you it's the most
powerful thing you'll ever learn in VI
you'll never have to make another plugin
again because you can run Shell Code
instead of a plugin and you can write
shell scripts as your Transformer
filters it's the single most powerful
thing in bi nobody knows how to use it
let me just show you what I just did so
yeah doing R exclamation point date is
nice and all but another way to do that
is to just memorize the following
memorize the following bang bang that's
it bang bang what does bang bang do bang
bang sends the current line to the
command and then replaces that line with
the output and that is where the power
comes let me show you this I'm telling
you nobody knows this you want to do
math okay you want to do some math let's
do scale uh scale equals 2 uh 3 /
whatever all right let's actually run
this through a calculator bang bang two
exclamation points and then run it
through bash actually no let's run that
one through BC boom it calculates it
well I set the scale as to two I I
screwed that one up let's do
multiplication it's easier uh but anyway
bang bang BC uh and now we get a number
right um You you you want to write code
that's going to generate it's going to
generate a list item for you for I in uh
one let's see one to 10 I don't know why
you would do this do uh do Echo I Su
whoops uh some done like why would you
possibly write bash code inside of your
Vim text file because watch bang bang
bash you run it and it bashes it
replaces the code with the output this
works for anything you want to stick a
calendar in here bang bang
cow okay you got a calendar in there you
you want to put I don't know you let me
show you some of the things I made uh
this is a thing now I want to I want to
Center this in the middle of the line
and I want to put it a common all around
it bang bang H title it's a shell script
I wrote it automatically does it okay
you don't need plugins people you can
use shell code and your own shell
scripts here's why it's more valuable to
do it as a shell script okay here's why
it's more valuable because when you
write it as a show script and use the
true Unix filter philosophy you can use
that thing elsewhere so let's say you
want to write a script elsewhere that
combines your filters by making a
transformation on text in a script you
can combine the two together in unix's
toolbox fashion let me show you so if I
say Echo some something here and I and I
and I pipe that to H title I get that
thing right and now I can use it no
matter what I can use I can use I have
all kinds of these I have now I have H
now I you know I have millions of
different commands isos SEC you know I
have you know if you want you can pull
down the current weather there there's a
ton of things that will allow you can
actually like go query a website using
raw stuff uh I have here's one I have um
the links A Links a what does links a do
links a pulls in when I so what did I
just do guys I did this I did bang bang
links a it ran the links a program and
replace the current line with the output
the links a program grabs the most
recent bookmark from My Links program
and sticks it in the document in a
formatted way let's say this you want to
write you want to write some uh I don't
know let's say let's say let's do that
for loop again where's that for Loop
okay let's say let's going to run the
for Loop bash right so we got the bash
now this is actually you know valid
markdown you don't know about markdown
yet but let's say you want to transform
that into HTML so let's do this
exclamation point right curly bracket
that says grab everything look down what
it did automatically I have to remember
any of that now I can send that to a
program called pandoc which will turn it
into
HTML see that okay what what if you want
to run JQ and you want to cor a thing
right the point of it is learn
Transformations the most powerful themm
command you will ever learn is two
exclamation points two exclamation
points so instead of this you should
learn this and you don't even have to to
do it it's just it's just this it's two
exclamation points exclamation point
this and another one if you want to send
it through the whole file so I actually
have I have a one that will take an
entire table it will calculate the
numbers and then put the number at the
bottom line of the text table there's
the numbers of these things are un
unfathomably unlimited you can and
you're using shell for all your stuff so
you didn't you don't have to have a
special Vim plugin manager to do this
you just use shell and then all of your
things can be combined together when
you're writing code later so let's say
you want to put all your pieces together
to like generate a report or something
all the stuff that you would have done
interactively with them from the command
line using the filter command can also
be used to put together these amazing
scripts for generating reports and stuff
uh so you do need all your sh scripts in
one place which is why I don't use sh
scripts I have Bonsai and it's all in a
single command so I have a command
called Bonsai and so anytime I make a
little shell script I put it together in
my monolith and my monolith is available
anywhere I can install it so I install
my monolith I cross compile and put it
on any system and I can use that if
you'd want to know more about that check
into Bonsai I'm writing a book about it
called Bonsai Beauty if you want to make
a single command instead of having a
bunch of shell scripts by the way your
argument about having to have all your
shell scripts with you is is the same
argument I could make against plugins
because neim has to have all those
plugins you have to install all them all
and and all it's no different you still
have the same problem right you're not
going to have all your favorite things
and and that's true the difference is is
that being able toar learn how to make
all this stuff name one plugin that
cannot be done through a filter and
there are many syntax based ones
treesitter things like that they make
total sense as plugins what doesn't make
sense as a plug plugin is a text
transformation of any kind and that
includes commenting by the way let me
show you a couple other things I hate
that people use visual mode I hate
visual mode I've always hated it and if
I want to comment these lines if I want
to comment this line I send it to the
filter and I say c
and it'll add a add a common in front of
it and then I undo it if I actually have
I have another one that actually when I
make a cut and paste actually paste it y
y y this actually Yanks it into a file
called temp buff and it puts it in my PB
copy so that I can copy it anywhere on
the system and that is not something
that happens in any other way so people
who use visual mode for those things are
giving that up you're giving that up
you're not you're not able to integrate
and have it do extra things when it's
doing this I can actually send this line
to my chat live by going bang bang we
and that will send it to my IRC chat
which is not running right now oh yes it
is there it is you guys just got it it
just got came across in my Wii
Chat so so there you are so I can send I
can send you URLs uh hey how you doing
and and so you know let's let me send
I'm going to send you this paragraph
boom boom We and I'm going to send it to
the program I send another line out and
see if that makes it nope what did I
send you a blank
I think I sent I think I sent you a
blank line and just try to try this okay
I can do undo there uh show prompts or
dur fls doesn't work so so yeah and then
so there you go uh so more on writing
files okay w w call on W you're going to
do it constantly to keep from losing
your stuff uh to get a listing of
director your files no you don't need
that that's totally stupid uh uh let's
see I let's see are shell prompt will
use LS if LS doesn't work
what uh shell
prompt uh I don't I don't need this I
don't need this for anything I don't I
don't know why I would ever do this
there's no point of
this it doesn't do anything I don't need
it remember we chat show prompt or it oh
oh right right right okay so anyway this
is um if you want this this is valuable
right here so if you want to write it as
a different file name so s temp uh which
is the place to write stuff usually temp
another you don't need the space By the
way um you can put it there that is
valuable um uh remove test now you can
remove it like this I would never do
that but I guess you could do that you
know why I wouldn't do that because I
can do this and I can I can remove it
this way I can I I'm like I'm like two
Taps away I'm AA away from removing this
without having to do all this extra crap
so I would never do this plus I also
have all my shell history here which you
don't have in Bim executing shell
commands from inside of Bim that are not
related to transforming the text is a
waste of time it's a total waste of time
because I can do it over here and I can
actually do it and I can back and forth
go over to the other thing rather than
doing this thing right here if I wanted
to remove I don't even remember what I I
saved out oh by the way um if you do
this and you can't remember what it was
uh you can push the up arrows but you
can't use Vim mode unfortunately so if
you wanted to see what your command was
you can do that so that was like what
was it I what I call it temp another so
if I want to do that I do remove temp
let's see remove temp stab another and
guess what I have tab completion which
you don't always have in viim sometimes
you have it sometimes you don't so you
know that's kind of unfortunate you also
don't get command completion which I
actually open an issue on in about
because there's like some of those
commands if you try to do them from the
command and Bim or neim it doesn't use
the completion that was set up by the
system but that completion is always
available here so and if you've got a
whole library of completers built like I
do for Bonsai then you want to be able
to use those completers but if you use
them from the the shell integration in
Vim or Neo you can't so it's always
better to have a pane or a window open
we can go over to do that okay so we're
almost to the bottom here I know this is
a long video it's much longer than I
planned um selecting text to write the
visual mode skip it I don't want to use
the visual if you want to learn visual
mode fine if you want to waste your time
doing it fine I think it's totally
stupid I think it's totally stupid use
visual mode I don't ever use it if
anything that I ever want to do is
either covered by a paragraph dap capap
or it's covered by right curly bracket
so right curly bracket will get all of
this so so if I wanted to like say yank
until the end of that whole section I
did yank and then curly bracket if I
want to send this entire thing to the
jet I can do
bang e exclamation point left curly
bracket and then type we and then that
goes to the input of my chat program
which goes to you so so that's my prefer
preferred way to do that um before you
press okay so so that's my I I I hate
visual mode I always have everybody
loves visual mode and I'm like why
number one visual mode doesn't work on
BI unless you have them so why and
number two how is it better you know
occasionally being able to do something
that edits all the things at the same
time is nice but it's so much better to
use something like CMT for that kind of
work you know like if you wanted to
comment this out you know bang bang CMT
and I'm commented it out it's just
faster it's actually faster than Vim
mode to do that so I I don't have any
intention to use visual mode for any of
that retrieving emerging files okay this
is valuable like if you wanted to grab
the file uh r
temp.go that will grab the file and dump
it in that is valuable it happens we use
it all the time
temp.go or whatever it'll dump the file
in where it's at that is valuable make
sure you learn that one um and uh so
let's see you can also read the output
of the external command for LS so yeah
you could do this R LS that's the thing
I mean I guess that has value the the
other way to do that is do LS and then
just bang bang bash but that's more
commands I guess I could see that it's I
guess I could see that I don't ever do
that but I could see doing that usually
because I want to do more than just one
command and maybe I want to modify the
command and I don't want to have to do
it on the command line so why not just
write the command out here you know uh-
La uh GP uh you know uh uh I don't know
you know what I'm saying I mean I don't
want to be I want to write my commands
in Vim I I don't want to be screwing
around on the command line I want to
write a command and then I want to pass
the command to bash and have it replace
it with its output if it was a thing
which it isn't
apparently let's try that so grep uh VM
right bang bang bash and that one's not
the thing I don't know why ls- a l maybe
it's because it doesn't have um let's
try this one bang bang bash the point of
it is is that I can actually transform
it you see what I can do if I had to do
that from the command line I'd have to
be constantly editing the command line
constantly constantly editing the
command line and I can just modify this
and say okay I want want to sort it okay
bang bang bash and another thing too
let's say I end up building up something
that turns out to be a script that I
want to have right watch this bang bang
W uh sltm
something right and now I've got it or I
can just do bang bang y y y which
automatically saves it to my temp buff
so why would I not do that so I can sit
here and edit the thing while I'm
looking at it and then I can actually
execute it by sending it to bash and and
that's far more powerful um uh so yeah
so anyway um that's my my take on that
uh command executes the external we
already covered this uh all right hey hi
are
home I'm I'm it just needs to be fluffed
up okay I need yeah okay you can do it
yeah all right so we're about done my
wife is home so I got to wrap up here
pretty soon uh uh use area veloc open
command open is is used all the time um
uh so open opens up a new line right
after the current line really common to
do this capital O opens a line above you
know so you guys remember the P pastes
after right and capital P pastes above
same thing with o o happens opens after
and capital O happens opens above so
those are very very powerful
particularly on the top line like I told
you like I'm doing a head-1 on my my
categories and you know upda you know
updating the top line is is always hard
I'm always like re fudging you know
moving things around so this is actually
a really great way to go about that so
hey thanks for the sub so let's go
through that and and now we're going to
go through o and then we got through the
aen command I already told you about a
pen a pen a just by itself is kind of
lame it just opens up the cursor right
where you are I never ever use this I
never use it I use i instead because
it's right where I want it to be a I
don't even remember a is like after it
why don't I just do I I just gotten used
to I being at the beginning and then I
just move my cursor one extra space who
cares one less thing to remember what is
important is capital A which we already
talked about right which goes to the end
of the current line um and we already
talked about the other line based things
capital D delete the whole line to the
end and capital c which controls which
changes to the end of the line so c g
see you know like a thing and then you
escape and it's like changed right so
we're going to go down some more we're
almost done another way to replace
capital r replaces to the end of the
line um
so uh I don't really understand this
command honestly uh I I've never used it
it's completely stupid don't why is this
even in the tutorial nobody uses this
has anybody ever used this no nobody
uses this it's totally don't
use this
don't use this use Capital C instead my
God how why would you use this
why would you use this because you
learned in the tutorial and you don't
know
better why not use Capital C I don't
understand I seriously don't
understand is it's what what is the
advantage of it I have never used this
command in my
life my skill issue I guess I it's
totally stupid I
know is is the insert of the line
so piss
you they hate to Hate to the replacers
there are dozens of
them replace word is
fine tell the replacers look replace
word is fine fine
yeah capital I just don't understand
capital r it's like I have no idea what
I'm even doing
here right
replace I still have to
escape okay wait a second okay let me
check this out
so like it was like I'm replacing word
Fu with K Bar super rare if it's I mean
I I'm I'm not getting it I I I guess I
guess what I just found out is that it
doesn't change the other stuff which I
guess is fine but if I was going to do
that I would do this I would do change
slsh and then I would type something new
and then I would be done with it that's
what I would do instead
that's my way of doing it you do it your
way I I use slash for everything like if
if I want to change up to one I do
C1 enter blah blah enter and then back
you know thing so I stupid I I would
never do that if you use it that's fine
I just never ever needed it why operator
I already told you about y Yip we
already covered it um you can yank words
it's rare but to do it you can do why
uh I don't know three
words and then it will just yank the
three words so that's the thing uh
visual mode sucks I'm not using that
move the cursor to the end of the line
uh dollar sign oh by the way so let's
talk about movement beginning of the
line is uh zero but there's also um what
is it um there's uh zero is the
beginning of the the the text on the
line zero is the beginning of the uh Z
is the beginning of the line and um and
carrot is the beginning of the first
word of the line and that's not covered
by the tutorial let me do that again so
if I want to go to the beginning of this
line and so dollar is always the end
always the end if you want to move to
the end like if you want to move and
you're not doing something right want to
move to the end that's actually kind of
valuable but if you you want to like go
to the beginning of the line and you
want to navigate to the beginning of the
line zero will get you at the very
beginning line you're not in insert mode
though and then uh carrot will get you
to the beginning of the line neither of
those are in insert mode though but they
don't copy this I don't think but
capital I will actually start inserting
at the beginning of the text of the line
all right so did you see what I said
there I use this constantly so a starts
writing at the end and capital I starts
writing at the beginning this is not
covered by the tutorial a is the end
capital A and capital I is the beginning
is the end in the beginning now you
could technically do um you could do
carrot right you could do carrot whoops
not car it you could do zero I and then
that would be the beginning of the
actual line so that's the beginning of
the actual line as opposed to um as
opposed to the rest so hopefully that's
there for you to go through um you can
use y as an operator y w Yanks one word
we know about that already the set
option okay set is used a lot set list
is probably my most common one so you
guys if you can see here all the totally
newbie things that are done this this
tutorial is here's another example of
how newbie it was right they mixed tabs
and spaces you see this they mixed tabs
and spaces in their in their
stuff I'm telling you it's a total
newbie tutorial so how do you see the
Extra Spaces right set no list set list
okay on occasion you need to paste
something and if you paste something and
you don't want it to do really screwy
things you might have to set paste most
of the other stuff you're not going to
need you want to set line numbers great
so set numbers there you go there's your
line numbers right uh you want to set no
no new now it take your line numbers off
uh set list is
on uh set no list turns off those things
so you work there are a bunch of things
in in um there are a bunch of things in
set that you're going to need to mix um
yeah I know they mix like Taps and
spaces here it's so bad because they did
the people who made the tutorial
obviously didn't know set
list so anyway uh set IC ignore case if
you want to change your case to not be
on you can do that um a lot of these
things are in the vmrc that we set up
and you can go read it if you want to
attempt to read it it took me 40 years
to be able to understand what was in my
vmrc but um but so there you go um
there's a summary that's lesson six
there's only one more lesson so oh is
really valuable open up at the beginning
of Line open up at the top of a line a
is super capital A is super good capital
I uh is super good right uh little a not
so much e goes to the end of a word I
don't ever use it unless you want to it
just makes you maybe faster spamming
through a thing I'm usually if I'm doing
that I'm usually searching for the word
to get to it if it's that far away I'm
not I'm not I'm not spamming you know
I'm not counting how many words that I
have to go I'm like I'm spamming or I'm
searching because it's faster uh capital
r replaces enters replace mode which is
whatever I don't know what that is we
talked about set ignore case and blah
blah blah we talked about filters most
importantly we talked about the filter
command the magic filter command which I
call it uh and then help so help this is
this is one of the places so exclamation
point help I'm sorry colon help gets you
into enb's amazing help uh I got they
the Vim help for en Vim is absolutely
amazing the first thing you're going to
ask is how do I get out right ship ZZ or
if you want co and qw Will get you out
there are other ways to close the buffer
but that way always works so you've
already know about it you know just two
Capital zzs will get you out of it and
you're good to go um uh line wise
comments otherwise I shift yeah but I
line wise comments I don't need I just
do like this CMT boom done yeah and if I
yeah so so that's what I do because
usually when I want to make a comment I
want to actually have the comment be be
you know I I I don't necessarily want to
comment sometimes I want to put other
things in front of it not to mention the
fact that I can pass it through a filter
that might want to increment the numbers
all the numbers in the front of it at
the same time it's just it's just a bad
idea to to program visual mode into your
brain I I I don't think it's I think
using filters instead is a far more
effective use of your mental memory than
than ever doing any of the other stuff
that people do with visual mode I have
never heard a compelling reason to use
visual mode in my life people tell me
all the time and every time like that
would be way more effective with three
keystrokes using my B filter instead um
but but yeah when when you switch
languages when I switch languages I just
use a different character yeah uh
CMT or whatever and but but my program
can know the the command it can know
what what the command is so I can just
do whatever yeah I can actually use it
so yeah I mean you know I mean you
there's a million other things that you
can do so the the point is look I'm not
trying to put if you want to use visual
mod that's fine you do you but I have
never found a compelling reason to use
it whatsoever and and I people love it
people it is really cool to have visual
mod on and have and be typing and have
everything updated at the same time it
almost is never practically useful it
really looks cool but it almost is never
as fast as just running something
through a really simple filter or just a
oneline bash script you know or a
oneline o script or something or you
know any anything
and and I I personally don't don't buy
into that uh every copy things is
nothing more yeah and if you're copying
things if you're copying things why are
you not just doing dap and and Yap dap
and Yap which I told you prime taught me
Yap is amazing Yap made me a whole made
a whole copy of that I Yap and dap all
the time now and and if I don't want you
know what else you can do you can do
exclamation point AP right so
exclamation point AP now it sends the
entire thing to a filter and now I can
send the entire paragraph to you
guys which is a lot it's now you're
going to get a lot of spam I sent you
like five lines sorry about that
everybody twitch I'm so sorry about that
long and short option names yes okay so
so getting help um I already told you
about the help you can get the help
about a certain thing uh something along
with the help that's very valuable for
people who like color is exclamation
point high this gives you all of your
colors okay if you want to see hey I
want my colors to match my other
terminal you can go in here and look at
the CSS value for the color and you can
p pipe through it and see what's going
on right there um there's another really
great Vim command um called
inspect um and I think inspect is it is
that it what is it called
inspect I thought it was
inspect um what's the one that shows you
what your syntax is I can't remember I
just learned it because I'm I've only
been using neim for like three weeks
everything I showed you is Works in Bim
and neim so far but that there's a
command there's a neim command that will
tell your context so you can see what's
causing the color if you care um anyway
create a startup script uh Bim RC you
already have one we we copied one over
you can go through and study that all um
and and you know that's in your dot
files you guys you already have it in
your dot files so you know um you have a
you have a MC and you have an an. Lua
you can go study these and start down
your your you know your life's work of
understanding what's in here um there's
a lot of stuff that I put in here that I
I one I used to go through this and
explain to everybody don't do that
anymore um you know like for example the
use of tabs there
so you know like see this right here see
the list characters this is like fancy
Or List characters uh set no lists so if
if you if you want to I mean if you want
to start gradually or board or something
you can go read through the MRC and and
look for different things in here um so
so so then you can start you know doing
all the other stuff um I do still extend
an invitation to you to learn Ed uh
which will make your you're much more
powerful that's anytime you type colon
you're entering nonvisual mode uh I
little known as X and so X is an entire
thing it's its own editor it can be
without you know anything else it's own
language and everything uh all the
substitutions everything we've been
doing using X mode so I do encourage you
to eventually go forward and learn that
um you never know you might only have Ed
or x on a system and havei some point um
and you might want to learn it but it
for most of you you're not going to need
it you definitely don't need it to learn
how to code completion um is a thing um
so this is a command line completion
with control D and tab so um
in order for me to show you this uh I
don't know why they put this in here
because it's not really anything you can
test here so um
fnt uh and so this it's actually not
correct if you put a tab right uh it'll
it'll start to give you your
thing um okay so I just hit tab tab and
now I can go down with n and up with p
and it'll show me my thing okay these
are um these are configured and they are
specific to the plug-in that we have in
for completion um I don't think that
they are necessarily Basics but they're
definitely worth learning now that we're
talking about them so we'll get more
into that as we start to code when we
get to coding we're going to get to that
this contrl D and tab um control D
doesn't always work for completion but
tab does tab generally does so if you
hit tab it I hit tab twice or as I said
you can hit control i instead and I'm
just learning this now so you go to the
end and do control tab tab and you you
can like decide you want to change it
and my hard part is I always want to do
Escape after that but that's not correct
right so so that's you can go try that
uh in your editing process um uh started
command E I don't use that uh I don't
use compatible mode this stuff is all in
the MRC don't need to mess with any of
that um we'll complete to the name edit
yes so completion you definitely want to
learn it talking to about help and
completion this concludes the vi Tor
that is all I am out of energy I've been
streaming for 5 hours today uh this is
the end of this video this is an hour
and 46 minute long Vim tutor run
everything that I feel like you need to
know about the basics of Vim is in this
video rerun it go through the Vim tutor
start editing on files and um the next
video that I make will be how to make
your code book and how to start taking
notes using Vim that you just learned
but you don't need it right now right
now you can just start messing with
files and practice doing anything you
maybe start writing some notes right
away and then we'll put that file into
your GitHub repo in the next segment but
that is it I'm going to go ahead and
stop the recording right now talk to you
later